# HENRIQUE VICENTE DE OLIVEIRA PINTO

henriquevicente@gmail.com

Website: https://henvic.dev

GitHub: https://github.com/henvic LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/henvic

**Summary:** Software engineer with 15 years of professional experience working in the software development industry, with an portfolio of several products and projects. Seasoned open-source software contributor with experience speaking at diverse events in Europe, South, and North America.

#### EXPERIENCE

### **Senior Software Engineer**

Nov 2023 – Present

Self-employed contractor

Remote

- Contractor with over 15 years of software engineering experience and 9 years with the Go programming language.
- Work with technologies such as Go, PostgreSQL, Elasticsearch/OpenSearch, Kubernetes, authentication/authorization with authorization with OAuth, authentication with OpenID, monitoring distributed systems with OpenTelemetry, Grafana, Terraform, Google Cloud, and Amazon Web Services.
- Implementation of new solutions adopting Go to match existing implementations to spec using reverse engineering.

# **Senior Software Engineer**

Aug 2022 - Apr 2023

Form3

Remote

- Worked in the Core Data team of the London-based Cloud-native Payment Processing Platform Form3 on internal services that handle payment and payment returns.
- Experience with Go, gRPC, NATS, PostgreSQL, Kubernetes, Terraform, and multi-cloud environments.

# **Senior Software Engineer**

Feb 2021 – Jul 2022

Stitch, PVH Corp.

The Netherlands

- Led a comprehensive project to enhance developer experience, ensure reliability, improve efficiency, and reduce operational costs by planning and implementing a robust automated testing infrastructure with fast integration tests (2s on average for the entire test suite) and replacing a non-relational database with PostgreSQL and Elasticsearch/OpenSearch.
- As part of the preceding goal, we yield a remarkable impact: a lasting expense reduction of over 90% of our recurring database cloud computing and licensing expenses and enhanced software development efficiency throughout multiple teams.
- Worked on multiple web services with API development with Go, Kubernetes, Terraform, and other technologies.
- Worked on data migration of media assets from renowned fashion brands, including internal clients such as Tommy Hilfiger and Calvin Klein and external ones such as Havaianas and Scotch & Soda.
- Experience with Go, gRPC, GraphQL, Kubernetes, Terraform, and Amazon Web Services.

### **Senior Software Engineer**

Jun 2019 - Jan 2021 **HousingAnywhere** The Netherlands

- On the platform team, worked public-facing RESTful APIs, internal services, and integration with affiliate partners.
- Worked on the payment system and payouts infrastructure with Stripe.
- Experience with Go, gRPC, Google Cloud Platform, Kubernetes, and microservices.

## **Senior Software Engineer Software Engineer**

Jan 2018 – May 2019 Mar 2014 – Dec 2017

Liferay, Inc.

Brazil

- As a key member of WeDeploy / Liferay DXP in its early days, led the development of its CLI tool, which was the primary client developers utilized to access and use the platform.
- Developed sophisticated solutions using Go and JavaScript for front and backend libraries and applications, such as reverse-engineering the socket.io protocol to use it for emulating an SSH connection.
- Worked on multiple front-end open-source programs, libraries, and frameworks maintained by the company for internal and external use.
- Experience with deploying desktop applications to end-users on multiple platforms (macOS, Linux, and Windows).
- Experience with function and integration tests for a diverse range of applications (web-based and desktop-based CLI tools for internal and external developers).
- Led the development of a CLI tool for managing GitHub very similar to today's GitHub CLI tool many years before an official tool had been released.

**Important:** For an extensive look at greenfield projects I've initiated independently or collaborated on during previous employment, as well as insights into my significant career, please visit my portfolio page on my website.

#### **EDUCATION**

### **Bachelor of Science in Computer Science**

October 2013 - December 2017

Universidade Federal de Pernambuco

### **EMC Academic Associate**

2017

Cloud Infrastructure and Services

#### **HIGHTLIGHTS**

**Interests**: Open-source software, Software Engineering, Photography, Nature, Skiing, Drones, Homelab, Airplanes, Industrial Design, Electric Vehicles (EV), piano, music.

**Keywords**: gRPC, Protobuf, HTTP(S), REST API, Go, JavaScript, Java, Unix scripting, cloud computing, Kubernetes, CI, CD, SQL, PostgreSQL, OpenSearch, Elasticsearch, Terraform, Grafana, Security, dev tools, DNS, networking, Linux, macOS, FreeBSD, VMware ESXi, golang.